"How to Get a Good Night's Sleep
Without Sleeping Pills"
In the Harvard Nurses' Health Study,
women who got 5 or fewer hours
of sleep a night gained
about 6 pounds more
over the subsequent 16 years
than those getting 7 a night.
Even if that was all due
to the difference in sleep,
that's still only 6 pounds
for 10,000+ more hours of sleep.
If even a tiny fraction of that time
was spent on diet and exercise,
you know, biking
to the nearest farm stand,
more weight could have been lost
in 16 weeks than in those 16 years.
Every little bit helps, though,
and getting at least seven hours
is healthier for you anyway.
This biggest reason to lose
sleep over losing sleep
is motor vehicle accident risk.
Driving drowsy increases your risk
of killing yourself and others.
People might think twice
about getting behind the wheel
after staying awake
for 48 hours straight,
but even just two weeks
of sleeping 6 hours a night
impairs your cognitive performance
as much as pulling two
all-nighters in a row.
So, what's the best way
to sleep better?
Sleeping pills are a nonstarter.
Those prescribed even
less than 18 pills a year
of so-called hypnotics,
the class of sleeping pills
that includes Ambien,
appear to have triple
the risk of dying prematurely.
Since up to 10%
of the adult population
is prescribed these drugs,
if the drugs really are killing people,
that could mean a six-figure
death toll every year.
Ambien's manufacturer
questioned the study,
but that's just one of dozens
of studies that found
a significant association
between sleeping pills
and premature death.
When the principal investigator
at the Scripps Clinic Sleep Center
was criticized for reporting
alarmingly high death risks
from these commonly
used medications,
he replied: "We can't hide risks,
even if they might frighten patients
out of taking hypnotics.
Patients have a right to know."
What's more, non-pharmacological
methods have been found
to work as good or
better than the drugs.
The recommended first-line
treatment for insomnia
is what's called
"cognitive behavioral therapy, "
which combines
conditioning techniques
to re-associate
the bed with sleep
and education surrounding
optimal sleep hygiene.
Here are the four rules
of sleep conditioning.
(1) Go to bed only
when you're sleepy.
(2) Only use the bed
for sleep (and sex).
No reading, eating,
or screen time.
(3) If you can't fall asleep
within about 15-20 minutes,
get up, leave the bedroom,
and don't come back
until you're sleepy again.
And repeat as necessary.
And finally (4), get up at
the same time every morning,
no matter how little sleep you get.
And although avoiding
napping is often added,
contrary to expectations,
the majority of research
does not show that daytime naps
interfere with nighttime sleep.
If there were four rules
of sleep hygiene I'd pick out,
it would be (1):
exercise regularly.
The best time to exercise
to improve sleep
appears to be 4 to 8 hours
before bedtime,
though it appears to be a myth
that exercising right before bed
is somehow disruptive to sleep.
(2) Avoid caffeine, nicotine,
and alcohol before bedtime.
We used to think as long as
you don't drink caffeine
in the evening,
it wouldn't affect sleep,
but four cups of coffee worth
even six hours before bedtime
can reduce total sleep time
by more than an hour.
Even just two cups in the morning
at 7 a.m. can change
what your brainwaves
look like on EEG that night,
though it's not clear if this
has any clinical relevance
beyond delaying the onset of sleep
by an average of 10 minutes.
Late afternoon alcohol consumption
(6 hours before bedtime)
may also impair sleep, even after
it's cleared out of your system.
And nicotine, whether from gum,
pill, patch, or cigarette, can also
have negative sleep effects,
though so too can
active nicotine withdrawal.
Food-wise, low fiber intakes and high
saturated fat and sugar intake
is associated with lighter,
less restorative sleep.
Meat intake is associated
with napping,
suggested as a proxy
for sleepiness.
This may be one of the reasons
insomnia has been reported
as a side-effect of low carb,
ketogenic diets.
Supplement-wise,
a single megadose of vitamin D
was found to improve
sleep duration and quality
in men and women
ages 20 through 50
with sleeping disorders.
And I've already talked
about melatonin-rich foods
and supplements
in previous videos.
(3) Make the bedroom quiet,
dark, cool, and comfortable.
Nocturnal noise can
adversely impact sleep
even if we're not
consciously aware of it.
Within a few days, you can
become habituated to noises
such that they don't wake you up,
but EEG studies and subjective
sleep surveys show the quality
of your sleep can still be affected.
Thankfully, ear plugs and sound
masking, like white noise machines,
have been shown to help.
And finally (4),
establish a relaxing
bedtime routine.
Relaxation techniques such as
massage, mindfulness meditation,
and soothing music may also help.
So may taking a relaxing
hot bath or shower.
One of the reasons late-night
eating can delay sleep
is that it may interfere
with the drop
in core body temperature that
normally occurs about bedtime.
That's thought to be one
of the cues that it's time for bed.
So, should you not take
a hot bath before bed?
No, because as soon as you
step out of the bath or shower,
the rapid decline in skin
temperature can accentuate
the natural nighttime
drop and improve sleep.
Even just a warm foot bath
may help you fall asleep
about 15 minutes faster.